Good
morning. It is Sunday morning, the 25th of תמוז, Tammuz, and we
are on נדרים מ"ט עמוד א', Nedarim Mem-Tet Amud Aleph, right at
the beginning of the sixth פרק, perek, הנודר מן המבושל. Hanoder Min
Hamvushal.
This פרק perek is going to be talking a lot about different
לשונות lishonot of נדרים, nedarim, different kinds of word choices that are
going to play a role in determining what the נדר neder actually
applies to or not. So sometimes it could be the difference between
a noun and a verb, and the noun is going to be
more inclusive or less inclusive or the verb will be more inclusive
or less inclusive. So we'll have to see some of the examples.
And the משנה mishna begins, הנודר מן המבושל, Hanoder Min Hamvushal, if
someone takes a נדר neder not to eat
cooked
food,
מותר בצלי ובשלוק, mutar bitzali uvshaluk, it is permitted to eat roasted
food, roasted meat, or שלוק, shaluk, stewed food.
It is very specific. So number one, we know these words, if
we pay attention in the משנה mishna in פסחים Psachim at the
tenth פרק, perek, the משנה mishna notes there were three or four
or five questions at the סדר seder in the time of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and one of them was about roasted meat,
that on all other nights we eat בשר צלי שלוק ומבושל, basar
tzali shaluk umvushal, we eat roasted meat or stewed meat or boiled
meat, however on the night of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach we
only eat the roasted meat. And the question of קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach is going to come back actually in the סוגיא sugya just
now, it's going to be an interesting contradiction perhaps some of the
Bible scholars in the room may have had some experience with this
topic, so we'll get into that a little bit later. Okay, so
that's the first line. If you take a נדר neder not to
eat cooked food, that does not include roasted or stewed foods because
they're not boiled. מבושל mvushal sounds like it means precisely boiled but
not any other method of preparation. אמר קונם תבשיל שאני טועם, Amar
konam tavshil sheini toeim, what if a person says a קונם, konam,
a נדר neder that I'm not going to taste a תבשיל, tavshil,
so not מבושל, mvushal, a food that was cooked, but a תבשיל,
tavshil, which means a dish, but again is from the same root
from בשל, bashel, so a boiled dish perhaps שאני טועם, sheini toeim,
אסור במעשה קדירה. asur b'maaseh kederah. He is אסור במעשה קדירה רך,
asur b'maaseh kederah rach,
he's not allowed to eat a food prepared in a pot, מעשה
קדירה, maaseh kederah, which presumably again is some kind of a porridge
or a stew, we're going to get into that in the גמרא
gemara as well, but he is forbidden from eating מעשה קדירה רך,
maaseh kederah rach, a liquidy or soft one, ומותר בעבה, umutar b'aveh,
but it's permissible to eat a very thick one, presumably because that
would not count as a תבשיל. tavshil. We're going to see that
the גמרא gemara is going to assert the word תבשיל tavshil means
something that you eat with bread and since you only eat a
thick, thick מעשה קדירה maaseh kederah by itself but not with bread,
that wouldn't count as תבשיל, tavshil, it's something else, it's called מעשה
קדירה maaseh kederah but it's not called תבשיל, tavshil, and therefore it
would not fall under the category of this נדר. neder. So we're
going to see that already it's very important what the person says.
The laws of נדרים nedarim take what a person says very seriously.
It's not just some abstract halachic category, it actually is what the
words that you say, what do they mean. However, so a person
says קונם תבשיל שאני טועם, Konam tavshil sheini toeim, מותר בביצת תרמוסא,
mutar b'veitzat turmusa,
permitted to eat this kind of prepared egg, I think it means
something like a poached egg, ובדלעת הרמוצה, uvidlat hamrimutza, and some other
kind of stewed squashes, stewed pumpkin of some kind.
הנודר ממעשה קדירה, Hanoder mimaaseh kederah, if a person takes a נדר
neder not to eat מעשה קדירה, maaseh kederah, meaning not from not
tasting תבשיל, tavshil, but now a person says a נדר neder to
not eat מעשה קדירה, maaseh kederah, אין אוסר אלא במעשה רתחתא, ein
oser ela b'maaseh ritachta,
he's not forbidden to eat anything except something which was really boiled
in a pot. So now there're two different things, one is something
which was boiled in a pot and one is foods, much broader
category of foods. תבשיל tavshil includes many different kinds of side dishes
of the meal that go with the bread,
and so that would include מעשה קדירה, maaseh kederah, מעשה קדירה maaseh
kederah is a smaller subcategory than תבשיל. tavshil. אמר קונם היורד לקדירה
שאני טועם, Amar konam hayored lekederah sheini toeim,
what if a person says קונם, konam, a נדר neder that I'm
not going to eat anything that goes into a pot, היורד לקדירה,
hayored lekederah, anything that goes into a pot, אסור בכל המתבשלים בקדירה,
asur bechol hamitbashlim b'kederah, then he's forbidden to eat anything which gets
cooked in a pot. So it's not about the type of dish
but it's about the method of preparation. And that's really the difference,
how do people talk about kinds of foods. If I'm taking a
נדר neder not to eat casserole or I take a נדר neder
not to eat stew is different than saying I'm taking a נדר
neder not to eat anything that is cooked in a pot. And
because the words that they used for stews or side dishes and
food cooked in a pot are very similar, that's where the overlap
that this משנה mishna is dealing with comes in. So basically different
kinds of foods, some more inclusive, some less inclusive, that are precisely
determined by what type of לשון lashon you actually use for the
נדר. neder.
We saw earlier in the מסכתא masecheta the fact that we say
סתם נדרים להחמיר, stam nedarim le'hachmir, if you just take a נדר
neder סתם, stam, you don't specify what it's referring to, we would
generally think that that's very
inclusive, we try to be מחמיר. machmir. So those are also interesting
points about how do we determine the what was actually included in
the נדר neder based on a person's choice of words. On the
one hand, if you don't specify it at all, then we should
be very מחמיר machmir because who knows what you were talking about?
As soon as you tell us, then we trust you.
So, and it doesn't have to be within a few seconds. It
can be exactly.
ופירושן, u-perushan, the explanation of what you meant to include could be
even much later once someone comes and asks you, "Oh, didn't you
take a נדר neder not to eat this kind of תבשיל?" tavshil?
and you say, "Oh, but I really meant it only applies to
this." So that's a very interesting question. So now the main point
of the גמרא gemara is Rabi Oshaya. תניא רבי אושעיה אוסר ואף
על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר. Tanya Rabi Oshaya oser v'af
al pi she-ein raya l'davar zecher l'davar. So what is Rabi Oshaya
forbidding? Rabi Oshaya is forbidding what the first line in the משנה
mishna allowed. The first line in the משנה mishna said if you
take a נדר neder from מבושל, mevushal, something boiled, that does not
include מותר, mutar, it is permitted בצלוי ובשלוק, b'tzalui u-v'shaluk, that the
person would be allowed to eat roasted or stewed meats. But רבי
אושעיה אוסר. Rabi Oshaya oser. Rabi Oshaya says stewed and roasted meat
would still be forbidden. Why? And he says even though אף על
פי שאין ראיה לדבר, af al pi she-ein raya l'davar, I don't
have a good proof, זכר לדבר, zecher l'davar, I have a אסמכתא,
asmachta, we're going to see the גמרא gemara says it's an אסמכתא,
asmachta, he has some kind of a hint at his point of
what he's trying to say based on the פסוק pasuk from דברי
הימים, Divrei HaYamim,
the thirty-fifth chapter of second Chronicles.
So the פסוק pasuk says ויבשלו את הפסח באש כמשפט. vayivashlu et
ha-Pesach ba-esh kamishpat.
פסוק Pasuk says they sounds like they boiled the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach on the fire. Well, it obviously can't mean boiled. Therefore, it
must mean roasted. And we see that the word ויבשלו, vayivashlu, they
cooked it, can be a more general term for cooking, including roasting,
כמשפט kamishpat according to the laws of קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. We
know that there's a מצוה mitzvah that the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
has to be roasted.
Interestingly enough, it's from the actual מצות לא תעשה. mitzvot lo taaseh.
It says לא תאכלו ממנו נא ובשל מבשל במים. lo tochlu mimeno
na u-vashel mevushal ba-mayim.
Don't eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach raw or boiled in water.
And therefore from that מצות לא תעשה mitzvot lo taaseh we learn
it has to be roasted כי אם צלי אש, ki im tzali
esh, it has to be a roasted on the fire. So question
comes up,
part of the question is fine, okay, this פסוק pasuk is from
דברי הימים, Divrei HaYamim, but the גליון הש"ס Gilyon HaShas Rabi Akiva
Eiger says, 'I don't know what you're talking about, there's a פסוק
pasuk from דברים Devarim that says something very similar.' Right at the
bottom, גליון הש"ס, Gilyon HaShas, שנאמר ויבשלו את הפסח קשה לי אמאי
לא מייתי מקרא בתורה בפרשת ראה גבי פסח ובשלת ואכלת. shene'emar vayivashlu
et ha-Pesach kasha li amai lo maiti mikra ba-Torah b'Parshat Re'eh gabei
Pesach u-vishalta v'achalta. The פסוק pasuk in פרשת ראה Parshat Re'eh
talking about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach also uses the word לבשל
levashel to cook, to boil the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. And that's
something that has troubled the Bible scholars somewhat because some Bible scholars
use this as a proof that דברים Devarim and שמות Shemot had
some kind of a contradiction. One says you could even boil the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and one says you have to roast it.
But it seems obvious again from this discourse that throughout תנ"ך Tanach
the word לבשל levashel means to cook, even more generally. That's Rabi
Oshaya's proof, proof from דברי הימים. Divrei HaYamim. And further, other מפרשים
mefarshim as well note that in דברים Devarim the תורה Torah is
also talking not only about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach but also
about the קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagigah because it says you can bring
the קרבן פסח צאן ובקר. Korban Pesach tzon u-vakar. And we know
that the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach has to be a sheep because
it's obvious from שמות Shemot
and everywhere else where the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is mentioned. And
so the fact that it mentions
בקר bakar cattle as well, the cattle is a... must be for
the קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagigah which accompanies the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
and that since it's a קרבן שלמים Korban Shelamim would be boiled.
So those are different explanations for why they're using the word לבשל
levashel to either refer to a different קרבן korban or it actually
is just a more inclusive term for cooking in general, which is
what Rabi Oshaya is saying. So גליון הש"ס Gilyon HaShas Rabi Akiva
Eiger is asking how come they didn't just use a פסוק pasuk
from דברים? Devarim? Why did Rabi Oshaya quote from דברי הימים Divrei
HaYamim instead of דברים Devarim even though both פסוקים pesukim make a
similar point? Okay, so it says לימא בהא קמיפלגי, leima b'ha kamiflagi,
דרבי אושעיה סבר הלך אחר לשון תורה. d'Rabi Oshaya savar halach achar
lashon Torah. Rabi Oshaya says נדרים nedarim must follow לשון תורה. lashon
Torah. It means what a word means in the תורה. Torah. That's
the halachic meaning. And therefore if you make a נדר neder not
to eat מבושל, mevushal, something cooked, since the תורה Torah uses the
word לבשל levashel to include roasted meat, even though normal people would
not say it that way, then Rabi Oshaya says those would even
be included. Interestingly enough, he's saying אחר לשון תורה, achar lashon Torah,
he's following the לשון תורה להחמיר. lashon Torah l'hachmir. He's coming to
include more things in the prohibition of the נדר. neder. It's interesting
to wonder whether Rabi Oshaya would also say that we follow לשון
תורה lashon Torah even להקל, l'hakel, even to be more lenient, would
we follow the תורה's Torah opinion the way the word is used
in the תורה. Torah. ותנא דילן סבר בנדרים הלך אחר לשון בני
אדם. V'tana dilan savar b'nedarim halach achar lashon bnei adam. And the
תנא tana of our משנה mishna who contradicts who disagrees with Rabi
Oshaya holds that for נדרים nedarim we follow the way people use
language. The way people use the word, that's what the word means.
It's colloquial, it's in context. And again, that gets into the מחלוקת
machloket that we saw in the first פרק perek about כינויי נדרים
kinuyei nedarim when you use different word in place of the word
נדר neder or קרבן, korban, קונם, konam, קונס, konas, all these different
words. Are those
לשון שבדו להם חכמים lashon she'badu lahem chachamim that the rabbis invented
fake words in order that people shouldn't take the word נדר neder
or קרבן korban lightly? Or are they just translations of the word
into other languages that happen to sound similar and therefore really is
just the way people talk? People use foreign loan words in their
normal speech. So those again, we're getting to the question: נדרים, nedarim,
is it something that the תורה Torah created? It comes from the
תורה, Torah, it's a halachic concept and people just start doing it?
Or is the fact that the תורה Torah has מצוות mitzvot about
נדרים nedarim recognizing the fact that this is how people speak, this
is something people do? Religious people take vows sometimes, therefore the תורה
Torah grants them significance and notes which הלכות halachot apply to them?
But then it really would be focused on actually what people are
saying and what they mean by it. Okay, so that's a מחלוקת
machloket between רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah and the תנא tana from the
משנה Mishnah is whether we follow לשון תורה lashon Torah or לשון
בני אדם. lashon bnei adam. לא, La, so now we said no,
it's not really like that. לא, La, דכולי עלמא בנדרים הלך אחר
לשון בני אדם. dekulei alma binedarim halacha achar lashon bnei adam. Really
everyone holds that we should follow what people say, meaning even רבי
יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah who we thought held לשון תורה, lashon Torah, even
רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah agrees that נדרים nedarim have to follow the
way words are used colloquially. Okay,
מר כי אתרא ומר כי אתרא.
mar ki
atra umar ki atra. Each was following the way people use the
word מבושל mevushal in their own place. רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah where
he lived, the word מבושל mevushal was used as a more general
term for cooking, the way even I think people in modern Hebrew
do nowadays. And the תנא tana from the משנה, Mishnah, where that
תנא tana lived, we don't know who it was, but the תנא
קמא Tana Kamma of the משנה Mishnah was saying מר כי אתרא,
mar ki atra, he was following the way it was used in
his place where the word מבושל mevushal means specifically boiled. Yes.
I'm not a biblical grammarian or vocabulary scholar but in that verse
from דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim immediately after that quote that he gave
here, they use ויבשלו בסירות ובדודים ובצלחות vayeivashlu basirot uvadvadim uvatzei lachot
so it looks like in דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim they are using
מבושל mevushal to mean any kind of cooking. So that's for now
it's definitely a good question. Again, whether it could even be, you
know we have something we call a pot roast. Yeah, right. And
so pot roast is roasted but it's in a pot with some
liquid and the question
of can you do your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach as a pot
roast or not comes up in פסחים Pesachim I think we must
have been a little while ago. Yeah, I remember, I don't remember
the answer though. I actually don't remember either. We'll have to go
back and check. So I think it's not allowed because I think,
well I think no, I think it's a מחלוקת machloket actually because
there's a debate whether it has enough liquid that it really is
problematic or not. It comes up in, not trying to remember we
saw this recently. It's another גמרא. Gemara. I don't remember off the
top of my head, I remember seeing it recently. It came up
in a different context. Okay. But yeah, so that's the question is
sort of the fine line between מבושל mevushal and צלי, tzali, what's
in between? We have something that's a pot roast, something that's this,
so what gets included? That's really the question. And again, even according
to רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah because, well as we just saw, right,
רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah doesn't even hold דבר תורה, d'var Torah, he
only holds, he even holds לשון בני אדם. lashon bnei adam. It's
just מר כי אתרא mar ki atra and therefore what do we
say? כי אתרא. Ki atra. באתרא דתנא דילן Be'atra de'Tana dilan according
to the תנא Tana of the משנה, Mishnah, לצלי קרו ליה צלי
ולמבושל קרו ליה מבושל. letzali karu lei tzali umevushal karu lei mevushal.
באתרא דרבי יאשיה, Be'atra de'Rabbi Yoshayah, in the place of רבי יאשיה,
Rabbi Yoshayah, אפילו צלי קרו מבושל. afilu tzali karu mevushal. They even
call roasted מבושל, mevushal, cooked, and therefore cooked is more general. והא
קרא נסיב לה אסמכתא בעלמא. Ve'ha kra nasiv lah asmachta be'alma. The
fact that רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah quoted a פסוק pasuk from דברי
הימים Divrei HaYamim is just an אסמכתא. asmachta. It's אסמכתא בעלמא asmachta
be'alma and therefore, and remember רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshayah even said I
don't have a ראיה לדבר, ra'ayah l'davar, it's only זכר לדבר. zecher
l'davar. So we have to question the fact, is that really a
real proof? It's not really a real proof, it's an אסמכתא בעלמא.
asmachta be'alma. He's saying it's זכר לדבר, zecher l'davar, it's a way
to remember his point or it's a mnemonic, it's some kind of
a way. The question of why is there this concept of אסמכתא
asmachta in general? We know that there are מצוות דאורייתא mitzvot d'oraita
which are learned out of פסוקים, pesukim, we know that there are
מצוות דרבנן mitzvot d'rabbanan which the rabbis introduced. So why is it
that sometimes the rabbis introduce their own הלכות מדדרבנן halachot mid'rabbanan and
then pretend so to speak that they're based on פסוקים pesukim with
an אסמכתא, asmachta, is connecting the rabbinic idea to a verse from
תנ"ך? Tanakh? And there's a relatively significant comment of the ריטב"א Ritva
in מסכת ראש השנה Masechet Rosh Hashanah where the ריטב"א Ritva is
talking about this whole question of אסמכתא. asmachta. It sounds like from
the גמרא Gemara in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah there that the זכרונות
מלכויות ושופרות zichronot malchuyot veshofrot on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah may be
a חיוב דאורייתא. chiyuv d'oraita. Right, at least according to רש"י Rashi
there, and the ריטב"א Ritva is saying no no no, it's אסמכתא,
asmakhta, and then the ריטב"א Ritva goes to explain well what does
it mean אסמכתא, asmakhta, and the ריטב"א Ritva says it's not some
kind of word games, it's not some kind of a joke that
the rabbis are playing. No, that's really the whole point of תורה,
Torah, that God included in the words of the תורה Torah the
opportunity for the rabbis to then use those words to connect to
rabbinic ideas. So when the rabbis have found a hook or connection
for rabbinic idea in the text, the point of אסמכתא asmakhta is
to really show that תורה שבכתב Torah she-bi-khtav is so all-inclusive and
it includes the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh and that's I'm
again part of the question of why there are these דרשות. drashot.
If we had all of these הלכות halakhot orally then how come
some of them had to be attached to דרשות? drashot? Becomes the
question of well many of those הלכות halakhot they wanted to do
that just to show you that the תורה שבכתב Torah she-bi-khtav has
the pluripotency, the capability of giving rise to even the תורה שבעל
פה Torah she-be'al peh as well. And there we have it. So
that's אסמכתא בעלמא. asmakhta be'alma. So that was the first part in
the גמרא, Gemara, רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya disagrees with the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma about what is included. A person is נודר noder מן
המבושל, min ha-mevushal, we thought maybe רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya holds by
נדרים Nedarim we should follow דבר תורה devar torah and we said
no, everyone agrees that it goes by לשון בני אדם. lashon bnei
adam. However, they actually have a מחלוקת machloket about the מציאות. metzi'ut.
They just live in different locales where the words are used differently,
so both of them are right. Each of them is right in
their own place where a person mean we follow what a person
means in that place and it happens to be that in their
different places they use for word מבושל mevushal differently. What's בעלמא be'alma
mean? בעלמא be'alma just just, just an אסמכתא. בעלמא, asmakhta be'alma, in
the world, but it means in this case אסמכתא asmakhta. בעלמא, be'alma,
it's nothing but an אסמכתא. asmakhta. קונם תבשיל. Konam tavshil. Now we
said, a person who took, now second part of the משנה, mishna,
קונם תבשיל שאיני טועם. Konam tavshil she-eini to'em. A person says I
take a נדר neder not to taste any תבשיל, tavshil, a side
dish or a dish at the meal. We'll have to see what
the word תבשיל tavshil means. הא מתבשיל נדר, ha mitbashil nadar, didn't
he, sorry, הא מיתבשיל נדר, ha mitavshil nadar, he took a נדר
neder from תבשיל, tavshil, mean how come you don't just say why
is it תבשיל שאיני טועם tavshil she-eini to'em and why does it
not just קונם תבשיל עלי Konam tavshil alai or something like that?
Okay, אמר אביי, amar Abbaye, האי תנא כל מידי דמתיכל בריפתא תבשיל
קרו ליה. hai tanna kol midei de-mitakhal be-rifta tavshil karu lei. This
תנא tanna is saying that anything that gets eaten with bread is
called תבשיל. tavshil. Meaning not any cooked food, it's not just any
מתבשל, mitvashal, any cooked food. No, תבשיל tavshil means specifically something that's
eaten as a side dish to bread. This has important consequences להלכה.
le-halakha. We know that in general, at least the way we פוסקן
pasken nowadays, is that anything that we eat in the meal at
at the meal you serve it at the table is included when
you make המוציא hamotzi that you don't have to make a separate
ברכה. brakha. But the way the גמרא Gemara phrases that is the
ברכה brakha on the פת pat is פוטרת התבשיל, poteret ha-tavshil, it
exempts the recitation of ברכה brakha on the תבשיל. tavshil. If we
follow this גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim it sounds like that's really
only things that are actually eaten along with the bread. Not just
eaten at a meal with bread. It sound right, כל מידי דמתיכל
בריפתא, kol midei de-mitakhal be-rifta, anything you eat bread really in it,
you dip the bread, you put it on a bread to have
a sandwich, something like that. That becomes interesting question להלכה. le-halakha. I
heard a story about רבי אהרן ליכטנשטיין זכר צדיק לברכה Rabbi Aharon
Lichtenstein zecher tzadik livrakha that at one time he was at a
wedding or something they served melon some kind of something as a
salad course and he took a roll and put the piece of
melon on the roll in order to avoid the מחלוקת machloket or
to avoid the question of whether or not he should have to
say a ברכה brakha on the melon or not. So certain people
are more careful about this than others. I think generally the מנהג
minhag is just to not worry about it too much. We say
more or less everything that comes during the meal. Dessert is a
separate question, certain kinds of appetizers maybe a different question, פוסקים poskim
get into that talking about things that are there to whet your
appetite but you don't actually get satiated from. Definitely things that are
for dessert on many occasions will require a separate ברכה brakha as
well because not really part of the meal, it's some kind of
a separate addition. Okay, מידי דמתיכל בריפתא. midei de-mitakhal be-rifta. Including food
of the seven species? If it's during the meal? So this is
again how do you read the גמרא. Gemara. One of the examples
from the גמרא Gemara was that they would bring out olives. And
the גמרא Gemara seems to say that you should have to say
separate ברכה brakha on olives that are served as because it's not
part of the meal, it's like after the meal. That was sort
of their dessert, they would have, you know, in France they have
salad for dessert, so in the times of the גמרא Gemara they
may have they had olives for dessert. So a question of what
is it about the olives? Is it because like you're saying it's
because of its from the seven species? It's halakhically significant status, a
higher level of fruit? Is it because it's not there to fill
you up but it's there just because you enjoy the flavor? Is
it because it's dessert, it comes after the meal is already over
and it's something additional? So this gets into the whole question about
cake. Do you have to say a separate ברכה brakha on cake?
If people serve tea at the end of the meal should you
have to say separate ברכה brakha on tea? What about if people
have different kinds of drinks at the meal? All different questions like
that. It gets tricky, some people prefer to end their שבת Shabbos
meal before dessert. And serve dessert afterwards, but it gets into a
whole situation, we won't have to go into it now. Another שיעור,
shiur, perhaps, exactly. What ברכה bracha you should say on dessert and
side dishes and all this. So, והא מתבשיל נדר, veha mitavshil nadar,
didn't he take a נדר neder from any תבשיל, tavshil, any cooked
food? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, האי תנא כל מידי דמתאכל בריפתא תבשיל
קרי ליה, hai tanna kol midi demitachal berifta tavshil karei lei, this
תנא, tanna, the תנא tanna of the משנה, mishna, saying anything that
gets eaten with bread is called a תבשיל. tavshil. Why? והא, veha,
so we're going to now see from the תוספתא Tosefta a different
perspective. והתניא, vehatanya, didn't we see in the תוספתא, Tosefta, והנודר מן
התבשיל אסור בכל מיני תבשיל, vehanoder min hatavshil asur bechol minei tavshil,
a person who takes a נדר neder not to eat תבשיל tavshil
is forbidden to eat every kind of תבשיל, tavshil, ואסור בצלי ובשלוק
ומבושל, veasur betzali uveshaluk umevushal, he's forbidden to eat roasted meat and
stewed meat and boiled meat, ואסור בהטריות רכות, veasur behitriyot rakot, and
he is forbidden to eat the squashes or the gourds of some
kind that are soft, שהחולין אוכלין בהן פיתן, shehacholin ochlin bahen ptan,
that sick people eat with their bread. So that sounds very inclusive.
Okay. איני, eini, והא veha רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah חלש, chalash, so
now we're going to ask a question that's going to go on
a huge tangent, which is a question of sort of medicine in
general, but the first question we're going to ask is, is it
really healthy for sick people to eat soft squash? Okay, right? Because
the תוספתא Tosefta last line said that sick people eat this soft
squash with their bread. איני, eini, so is that really true? והא
veha רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah חלש, chalash, על לגביה ההוא אסיא לאסויי,
al legabeih hahu asya leasuyei, חזא קרא דמנח chaza kara demanach בביתיה,
beveiteih, שקיל ונפק. shakil venafak. So when רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah got
sick, a certain doctor went to him to heal him. He saw
a gourd on the floor of his house and he freaked out
and he left. Okay, so the doctor presumably was expressing his displeasure
with רבי ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmiyah choice of gourds as a meal for
sick people, and therefore it sounds like this story contradicts the sense
from the תוספתא Tosefta that we got that sick people should be
eating soft gourd. Ah, so one point is that the רש"ש Rashash
I think, asks like what kind of a doctor is this? This
isn't the way you practice medicine. If someone's doing something unhealthy, you
don't just leave, you should give them good medical advice. You should
tell them, oh, it's not healthy for you to be eating this
and then continue. So it's an interesting question why did the doctor
freak out so much. Nonetheless, so what does the doctor say? אמר,
amar, the doctor says, אמר מלאך המות אית ליה לדין בביתיה, amar
malach hamavet it lei ledein beveiteih, you have the מלאך המות malach
hamavet in your house, you have the angel of death hovering in
your house, presumably because he was eating this food, this squash, ואנא
איעול לאסויי יתיה, veana eiul leasuyei yateih, and I'm going to try
to heal you? Like it's going to be a futile attempt, it's
going to be worthless because you're eating this unhealthy food and so
even though you called the doctor, but you're not correcting your... so
that sounds like what he should have said to begin with. Why
did he then first he went out? He went out of the
house and then he came back in or something, exactly, maybe he
spoke to him from outside the house. How long you gonna be
here? Because this caterer's coming right now to do some stuff at
safari. How long is he in the driveway? You want to move
it? No. He's saying right here, right here. He'll be here till
8:30 and then there's services downstairs. He'll be here till 8:30. Is
there a caterer? So what, you're not supposed to be in the
room? It's very hot in here. If we put the air conditioning
on, can you move to the room? No, the air conditioning's blown,
we're not doing that. We're gonna jump the unit. Can you move
to the room? Yeah. It's not going to cool off. Wait, wait,
listen. Give us till 8:30 because we're broadcasting here. Can you do
that? Yeah, we're in the middle of a broadcast. 8:30 move it.
Okay. Okay, לא קשיא, la kashya, it's not a question. הא ברכיכי
הא באשוני. ha berachichei ha beashunei. So this is talking, one is
talking about the soft flesh of the squash and one is talking
about the hard shell of the, you know, certain kinds of gourds
have a very hard shell. So that would probably not be good
for sick people to be eating, but the mushy soft part inside
probably is very good for sick people to be eating, it's very
easy to digest, something like that. Okay. רבא בר עולא אמר, Rava
bar Ulla amar, הא בקרא גופא הא בגבי, ha bekara gufa ha
beigabei, no,
רבא בר עולא Rava bar Ulla said
this was referring to the gourd itself and הא בגבי ha beigabei
this was talking about the shell of the squash. Sorry, the first
line is saying this is a soft one, this is a hard
one, meaning maybe the younger squashes are softer and easier to eat,
the older squash gets thicker and tougher. Or alternatively, it's whether it's
talking about the flesh of the squash as opposed to the shell.
So either of those opinions saying basically sometimes squash could be healthy
for you to eat when you're sick and sometimes not. Okay, הא
בגבי דקרא. ha beigabei dekara. אמר דאמר רב יהודה, amar deamar Rav
Yehuda, לולבי דקרא בסילקא לולבי דכתנא בכוכחא. lulavei dekara besilka lulavei dechitna
bechucha. It is good to eat לולבי דקרא, lulavei dekara, the shells
of the squash, in with beets. I don't really know what they're
talking about, but... I don't really know what they're talking about, they're
obviously talking about some kind of a vegetable dish I presume, but
the squash shells with beets, לולביא דכתנא lulvia di-khitna or the flax
stalks. And some say the seeds. Oh, the seeds. Yeah. Okay. The
seeds maybe. I'm not really expert on the cooking practices so I
would trust Steinsaltz more than me, or the stalks or the seeds
of something from flax with כותח. kutakh. כותח kutakh is the Babylonian
sauce that the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael אמוראים Amoraim expressed their great
disgust at how it tasted. It was made out of bread crusts,
possibly moldy bread crusts, and spoiled milk, sour milk. And it gets
discussed in פסחים Pesachim because a question of whether or not it
is in fact edible and whether the חמץ chametz that is used
in its production is really significant or not. Okay. ודבר זה אסור
לאומרו בפני עם הארץ. Ve-davar ze asur le-omro bifnei am ha-aretz. You're
not allowed to tell this to an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, meaning
this whole discussion about the squash, which kinds of squash are healthy
and which kinds are not, you shouldn't tell an עם הארץ. am
ha-aretz. So already sort of what are we talking about, what is
going to be a bad thing about telling an עם הארץ? am
ha-aretz? So the ר"ן Ran says it's because they're going to pull
up all of the flax plants in order to eat them because
you told them that it was a good thing to eat and
so that would end up being a bad thing. However, תוספות Tosafot
says no, they're going to make fun of the גמרא Gemara for
including all of this,
the עם הארץ am ha-aretz will make fun of the גמרא Gemara
because the גמרא Gemara includes this seemingly obscure medical advice about which
kind of squash to eat and doesn't seem relevant. And this is
something we see nowadays a lot, that people ask why is it
that you have all these strange stories in your גמרא, Gemara, why
do you have all this seemingly irrelevant medical advice in the גמרא?
Gemara? So that's in the גמרא Gemara and you don't have to
make fun of it.
And then,
we'll pause for just a
sec.
Okay. And the מפרש mefarish here actually has an alternative approach. And
the מפרש mefarish says who's an עם הארץ? am ha-aretz? Remember that
עם הארץ am ha-aretz has a very
well-defined category of people who are particularly malicious. The גמרא Gemara in
ברכות Berachot lists people who intentionally avoid certain מצוות, mitzvot, not wearing
תפילין, tefillin, not wearing ציצית, tzitzit, not learning תורה Torah regularly, things
like that. So if that's an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, then it
may be that we don't want to provide the medical advice to
someone who is an עם הארץ. am ha-aretz. Interesting suggestion as well,
a bit difficult to stomach for our cosmopolitan society perhaps. Okay. So
those are three different suggestions about why you wouldn't want to tell
an עם הארץ am ha-aretz about this סוגיא. sugya. רבא אמר מאן
חולין, Rava amar man kholin, so who are these חולין, kholin, who
are these sick people? רבנן. Rabbanan. It's the rabbis. It's not actually
sick people. It's the rabbis. So why would we say that the
rabbis are sick? A few possibilities, but we say רבא לטעמיה
דאמר רבא, Rava le-ta'ameih de-amar Rava, כמאן מצלינן אקצירי ואמריעי? ke-man matzlinan
ak-tzirei ve-amriei? Who are we praying for when we pray for קצירי
ktzirei and מריעי, mriei, which are basically both types of sick people?
So
and if you look in the מפרש, mefarish,
מצלינן אקצירי, matzlinan ak-tzirei, we pray for the sick because it says
רופא חולי עמו ישראל. Rofeh kholei ammo Yisrael. We say that ברכה
bracha in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei that God should heal the sick.
But מריעי, mriei, which also means sick people, על פליטת סופריהם, al
pleitat sofreichem, which is the ברכה bracha for the scholars. And therefore,
since we have a ברכה bracha for both scholars and the sick,
or the physically sick, and because they're both called sick, it sounds
like the rabbis are called sick. Okay. כמאן כרבי יוסי? Ke-man ke-Rabbi
Yosi? It's like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi's opinion, מדאמר קצירי ומריעי שמע
מינה קצירי קצירי ממש מריעי רבנן. mi-de-amar ktzirei u-mriei shema mina ktzirei
ktzirei mamash mriei rabbanan. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi who had the
opinion that strangely that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi has this opinion in,
I think, מסכת ראש השנה, Masechet Rosh Hashanah, that you shouldn't really
be praying for your personal needs throughout the year because it's all
determined already from the beginning of the year on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So the kinds of things that
you would have to be praying for, for health and wellness and
things like that, would have to be either things which have arisen
since then, but even then, you're going to get yourself in trouble
because it was already decreed against you from ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
time. So רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah suggests
some difference between a preventative prayer for the sick compared to something
that once a person has already gotten sick. You're not allowed to
דאוון daven a preventative prayer to keep from getting sick because if
you're going to get sick, that was already decreed against you from
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah time. But if you get sick, then you
could pray to get better. Alternatively, the other suggestion is the difference
between prayers for the יחיד yachid and prayers for רבים, rabbim, whether
it's a communal need, many, many sick people all together or one
individual sick person. And interesting to note that The exemption that we
have to say מי שברך Misheberach on שבת Shabbat for the sick
is also based on that principle that we're praying for communal need,
a public need for many people who are sick and not just
one person, we might not have a תהלים Tehillim gathering or something
like that for someone who's sick on שבת Shabbat because of that
reason that we're not allowed to do personal supplications and things like
that. But why would the rabbis be called sick to begin with?
So there's a relatively well-known מדרש midrash it's actually in the גמרא
Gemara in שבת Shabbat and it comes up פרשת חוקת Parshat Chukat
people talk about it a lot because the פסוק pasuk says זאת
תורת אדם כי ימות באהל. Zot torat adam ki yamut be-ohel. A
person who dies in a tent, this is the תורה Torah for
a person who dies in the tent. What does it mean? The
way to learn תורה Torah is a person kills kills oneself over
the study of תורה Torah that it's such a difficult process and
you really push yourself and you really try very hard, and you
tire yourself out and you become very weak. You can imagine someone
who's sitting, you know, studying however many hours a day and isn't
really eating enough and isn't really, you know, locked up in the
library or in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash that such a person's
not getting enough to eat, so they would become sick. They wouldn't
get enough exercise. And I think one of the מפרשים, mefarshim, I
forget who, explains this story from ריש לקיש Resh Lakish story, where
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan are in the
stream swimming, and then רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan convinces ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish that he should study תורה Torah and he was a big
strong guy, and then once ריש לקיש Resh Lakish agrees to study
תורה Torah that he loses his physical strength because he's already agreed
to be studying תורה Torah and תורה Torah because it's something for
your נשמה neshama and it's all of your energy is dedicated to
that, it really takes away your physical strength. People have written also
sociologically almost about different sort of what it means to be manly
in different communities and they noted that in the ישיביש Yeshivish community
particularly, to be manly can often mean to be, you know, what
the Western world would consider to be very weak nerdy kind of
person, someone who studies all day and wears glasses and sits and
is hunchbacked and pale skin from not being outside or something like
that, but that's really someone who is involved in studying תורה Torah
all day, that's really the ideal, not the big football player who's
out, you know, chopping wood and kinds of things like that, driving
a pickup truck.
Or like when the city is attacked and it's only being
protected because of this one תורה Torah scholar who is very weak
physically but then he gets killed in that.
I think it's a גמרא Gemara that comes up about the destruction
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right. So for example, you have a lot of
examples of that where you really see that physical weakness can often
accompany greatness in תורה. Torah. Many of the אמוראים, Amoraim, there's a
number of אמוראים Amoraim who were blind as well, something which made
it very difficult for them in their time to study but at
the same time presumably also made it difficult for them to work
in the field or things like that so they were able to
focus on their תורה Torah studies. Okay, so the משנה Mishna noted
now that we've said
that when you take a נדר neder not to eat a תבשיל,
tavshil, תבשיל שאיני טועם, tavshil she-eni toem, אסור במעשה קדרה רך, assur
be-maaseh kederah rach, you're not allowed to eat a liquidy מעשה קדרה
maaseh kederah pot soup of some kind, however עבה, ave, a thick
one, you would be allowed. So why are you allowed to eat
a thick one? מותר בעבה, mutar be-ave, מתני דלא כבבלאי, matni de-lo
ke-Bavlai, the משנה Mishna does not follow like the Babylonians, and this
is one of the great insults in the גמרא, Gemara, דאמר רבי
זירא, de-amar Rabbi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said, בבלאי טפשאי, Bavlai
tipshai, the stupid Babylonians דאכלי לחמא בלחמא, de-achli lachma be-lachma, they eat
bread with bread. What did they do? They would put their whatever
it is, oatmeal or something, not oatmeal but it was like a
porridge, wheat meal, barley meal, they made some kind of a porridge,
a hot cereal, and they would put it on bread. So it's
like imagine a potato knish, you have a dough which is stuffed
with potato. This is, you know, carb loading. הני בבלאי טפשאי, hanei
Bavlai tipshai, the stupid Babylonians that they eat bread with other bread,
meaning they eat carbs with other carbs. They don't make a sandwich
with meat on top of their bread, they put bread on bread.
And therefore
the משנה Mishna does not apply because that would be referring to
putting your עבה, ave, your thick מעשה קדרה, maaseh kederah, which would
be a thick porridge, and smearing it on bread, and therefore that
would fit into the category of תבשיל tavshil because that would be
a side dish that you eat with bread. So רבי זירא's Rabbi
Zeira point about the בבלאי, Bavlai, it must be that the משנה
Mishna does not follow Babylonian position and again that makes sense because
the משנה Mishna is written in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the
Palestinian Jews of the time rather than the Babylonian Jews and therefore
their eating habits may have been different, yes.
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was a Babylonian who made עליה. Aliyah.
So that's also a very important point, that רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
noted the error of his ways in his culinary choices. It's an
interesting point. We also see other גמרות Gemaras where the rabbis from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael make fun of the food, we mentioned already
the כותח kutach today, and also
the Babylonian rabbis make fun of the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael rabbis
for their choice. I think they make fun of, they had some
kind of a chicken dish that they thought was very disgusting. So
each of them makes fun of each other's foods, some of the
more humorous points in the גמרא, Gemara, breaks it up a little
bit. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda דמשקי. de-mashke. להון להני נקדני
דהוצל הדי דעתא. lehon lahanei nekdanei deHutzal hadei da’ata. So a person
who was asked if they להני נקדני דהוצל הדי דעתא
lahanei nekdanei
deHutzal hadei da’ata to take out the to eat the porridge, דייסא
da’itsa is porridge. So if you’re going to scoop it out, היכי
מעלי דמיכלא דחיטי בלחמא דחיטי. heichei ma’alei demichla dechittei belachma dechittei. Should
you eat the since they eat porridge on their bread. Now this
is a question. Which one goes with which? Do you eat wheat
porridge on wheat bread, ודשערי בלחמא דשערי udesia’arei belachma desia’arei and barley
porridge with barley bread, או דילמא דחיטי בדשערי ודשערי בדחיטי o dilma
dechittei bedesia’arei udesia’arei bedechittei and should you put or alternatively do you
put wheat porridge on barley bread and barley porridge on wheat bread?
רבא אכלי בחסיסי. Rava achlei bechasissei. רבא Rava ate it with his
fingers. So, okay? So far so good? Did Steinsaltz say that this
is either
barley flour or lentil flour? Lentil, what, that שערי se’irei may not
be barley. It may be lentil.
That’s interesting, that would make it a bit healthier, right? It wouldn’t
just be carbs, carbs, carbs, it would have some protein as well.
Yeah, they say it’s תוספות Tosefot quoting רבינו חננאל.
Rabbeinu Chananel. So that’s an interesting point. רבינו חננאל. Rabbeinu Chananel.
Normally
we would think that שעורים se’orim are barley, but again I would
trust Steinsaltz to do his research, Rabbi Steinsaltz for this. רבינו חננאל
Rabbeinu Chananel wasn’t in here. We don’t have him on the page,
he must be somewhere else. Yeah. So okay, so רבא אכלי בחסיסי,
Rava achlei bechasissei, רבא Rava ate porridge with his fingers, which sounds
a bit uncouth. רבה בר רב הונא אשכחיה לרב הונא דקאכיל דייסא
ב Rabba bar Rav Huna ashkeichei leRav Huna deka’achil da’itsa be sorry,
no, רבא אכלי בחסיסי Rava achlei bechasissei is the previous line. I’m
sorry. חסיסי, chasissei, now I forgot the word
חסיסי. chasissei. המלף פיתו בחסיסי ומפרשא לה במסכת פסחים. Hamalaf pito bechasissei
umefarsha lah beMasechet Pesachim.
חסיסי, chasissei, what, he would just dip his bread, is that what
it says? What does it say that רבא Rava רבא Rava said
he
had
it with the oh
wait, he would make it with the grain, just the roasted grain,
the toasted grain. So he ate a different kind of porridge. Okay,
fine. ורבה בר רב הונא. VeRabba bar Rav Huna. Now we get
to רבה בר רב הונא. Rabba bar Rav Huna. רבה בר רב
הונא אשכחיה לרב הונא. Rabba bar Rav Huna ashkeichei leRav Huna. רבה
בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna, this is רבה Rabba the
son of רב הונא Rav Huna found רב הונא. Rav Huna. Now
I don’t know if it’s the same רב הונא, Rav Huna, it’s
not his father. I think it’s a different רב הונא, Rav Huna,
but I’m not sure. Maybe רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav
Huna, it may be the same רב הונא, Rav Huna, in which
case it’s his father. He found him דקאכיל דייסא באצבעתיה deka’achil da’itsa
be’etzba’ateih and found him eating porridge with his
fingers. אמר ליה אמאי קאכיל מר בידיה? Amar lei amai ka’achil mar
beyadeih? Why is my master eating with his hands? Like this is
a bit uncivilized. Wow.
אמר ליה הכי אמר רב. Amar lei hachi amar Rav. Didn’t רב
Rav teach us, דייסא באצבעתיה
בסים? da’itsa be’etzba’ateih bassim? It’s really good to eat porridge with your
hands because it makes it taste better. בסים bassim is like a
flavor, that you get more of the eating experience when you eat
with your hands, you can feel the texture of the food, you
enjoy it more. וכל דכן בתרתין vechol doken bitartein and even more
with two fingers, וכל דכן בתלת vechol doken bitlat and even more
with three fingers.
These are Babylonian אמוראים. Amoraim.
Yes, and they whether you scoop it with one finger, scoop with
two, you scoop with a big scoop of דייסא. da’itsa. So I
don’t know what their, you know, they didn’t have, what is it,
that the fork was definitely not brought back to the Western world
from China until Marco Polo or something like this, so they didn’t
really have forks for eating with. I don’t know whether it was
spoons either, we’re going to see here someone’s eating with a stick.
So, you know, these were people who didn’t live in the same
kind of luxury that we have to have utensils and things like
that. So I presume the alternative would be just to pour the
porridge down your throat, that’s also not particularly pleasurable. So this way
you get to scoop it slowly, you get to enjoy it. Okay.
אמר ליה רב לחייא בריה.
Amar lei
Rav leChiaya breih. So רב Rav said to חייא Chiaya his son,
חייא Chiaya his son. וכן אמר ליה רב הונא לרבה בריה. Vehachen
amar lei Rav Huna leRabba breih. And so too רב הונא Rav
Huna said to רבה Rabba his son. So it is רבה בר
רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna, it’s the same רב הונא, Rav
Huna, it’s so רבה Rabba is the son of רב הונא, Rav
Huna, this רבה. Rabba. So רבה בר רב הונא בריה, Rabba bar
Rav Huna breih, מזמנין לך למיכל דייסא. mezamnin lach lemachal da’itsa. If
people invite you to eat porridge, עד פרסה, ad parsa, you should
go even a whole פרסה, parsa, you should travel a relatively far
distance in order to be able to enjoy this porridge with them.
Okay? למיכל בישרא דתורא. lemachal bisra detora. If people invite you over
for steak, עד תלתא פרסאי, ad tlata parsa’ei, you should go even
three פרסאות. parsa’ot. So that’s, you know, you should travel very far
to go to a good barbecue. It’s an interesting piece of advice
to keep in mind this time of year. אמר ליה רב לחייא
בריה. Amar lei Rav leChiaya breih. So another thing that רב Rav
said to חייא Chiaya his son, וכן אמר ליה
רב הונא לרבה בריה, vehachen amar lei Rav Huna leRabba breih, and
another thing that רב Rav said to חייא Chiaya his son and
also that רב הונא Rav Huna said to רבה Rabba his son:
כל מידם לא תפלוט קמי רבך לבר מקרא ודייסא שהן דומות לפתילה
של אבר ואפילו קמי שבור מלכא פלוט. kol midam lo tiflot kammai
rabbach levar mikara veda’itsa shehein domot leptila shel ever va’afilu kammai Shavor
Malka pelot. So you should not spit out your food in front
of your teachers except for two foods, קרא, kara, gourds, and דייסא,
da’itsa, the porridge. Interesting that these are the foods that we’ve been
talking about this whole סוגיא. sugya. It'd be interesting to see how
someone with a more academic bent would break down the סוגיא sugya
to see how the different pieces fit together, but not for now.
So you should not spit out your food in front of your
teacher except for gourds and porridge because they are like פתילא, ptila,
they are like פתילא של אבר, ptila shel avar, they're like the
the lead wire that they used to execute people by שריפה. sreifa.
The way they would kill people by שריפה sreifa would be to
melt a lead wire and pour the boiling hot molten lead down
their throats and so the פתילא של אבר, ptila shel avar, the
it's like when you eat these foods it really gets stuck in
your guts and it really weighs you down and lead is very
heavy, perhaps it's very painful, maybe it gives heartburn, I'm not sure
exactly what they're trying to hint at and therefore ואפילו קמי שבור
מלכא פלוט v'afillu kamei shavur malka pelot even in front of the
king you should spit it out, meaning again I don't know exactly
what they're talking about. If you intended to be eating gourds to
begin with I'm not sure why you're spitting it out, if you're
intending to eat the דיסא daisa why you're spitting it out, I
don't know again the eating practices or what this is really talking
about, but we can at least read through it. רבי יוסי ורבי
יהודה חד אכל דיסא באצבעותיה, Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Yehuda chad achal daisa
b'etzbaotei, so two of the great rabbis Rabbi Yose and Rabbi Yehuda
two of the great תנאים, tannaim, but now they're both called anonymously
here because they're having an argument about something which is basically relatively
uncivilized so we don't want to attribute which opinion to whom. So
one was eating the porridge with his fingers חד אכל דיסא באצבעותיה
chad achal daisa b'etzbaotei וחד אכל בהוצא v'chad achal b'hutza and one
was eating with a stick. אמר ליה דאכל בהוצא לדאכל באצבעותיה, amar
lei d'achal b'hutza l'd'achal b'etzbaotei, the one eating with a stick said
to the one eating with the fingers עד מתי אתה מאכילני צואתך,
ad matay ata ma'achileni tzo'atecha, why are you continuing to feed me
your waste? Because they didn't wash their hands presumably and so he's
eating with his hands, he's getting all sorts of horrible contamination into
the communal food. So he says back אמר ליה דאכל באצבעותיה לדאכל
בהוצא, amar lei d'achal b'etzbaotei l'd'achal b'hutza, so the one who's eating
with his fingers says back to the one eating with the stick
עד מתי אתה מאכילני רוקך, ad matay ata ma'achileni roka'acha, why are
you feeding me your saliva? Because he's double dipping, he's he's
eating
with the stick and it has his saliva on it and then
it goes back into the pot, so they're each criticizing each other
of contaminating the shared pot of of דיסא. daisa. It's also very
sticky, so even you can imagine that when you get it on
your hands it would pull off whatever kind of שמוץ shmutz you
had on your hands if you hadn't washed your hands. רבי יהודה
ורבי שמעון אייתו לקמייהו בלוספין, Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Shimon ayitu l'kameihu belusfin,
so Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon they brought before them the בלוספין.
belusfin. בלוספין belusfin is not clear what they are, perhaps it's some
kind of figs. המפרש hamefaresh says it's kind of some kinds of
figs that were very overcooked figs, stewed figs, okay. So רבי
יהודה אכל, Rabbi Yehuda achal, Rabbi Yehuda ate it, רבי שמעון לא
אכל, Rabbi Shimon lo achal, Rabbi Shimon did not eat the figs.
אמר ליה רבי יהודה מאי טעמא לא אכיל מר, amar lei Rabbi
Yehuda may ta'ama lo achil mar, so Rabbi Yehuda asked Rabbi Shimon
why are you not eating these figs? אמר ליה רבי שמעון אלו
אין יוצאים מבני מעים כל עיקר, amar lei Rabbi Shimon elu ein
yotzim mibnei me'ayim kol ikkar, these can never be digested or perhaps
they will take a long time to be digested, it's going to
fill up your your guts, you're going to be backed up. אמר
ליה רבי יהודה כל שכן שנשמוך עליהן למחר,
amar lei Rabbi
Yehuda kol shekein shenishmoch aleihen l'machar, no Rabbi Yehuda had a whole
reason for doing this, he said I want to eat these now
so that I'll still be full tomorrow. He wants to rely, he
doesn't want to have to eat breakfast tomorrow, so if he eats
eats these figs now then he won't be hungry tomorrow. רבי יהודה
הוה יתיב קמיה דרבי טרפון, Rabbi Yehuda hava yativ kamei d'Rabbi Tarfon,
so Rabbi Yehuda was sitting for Rabbi Tarfon אמר ליה רבי טרפון
היום פניך צהובים, amar lei Rabbi Tarfon hayom panecha tzehubim, Rabbi Tarfon
said to Rabbi Yehuda today your face is shining or is very
yellow. אמר ליה אמש יצאו עבדיך לשדה והביאו לנו
תרדין ואכלנום בלא מלח ואם אכלנום במלח כל שכן שהיו פנינו צהובים,
amar lei emesh yatz'u avadecha lasadeh v'hevi'u lanu tardin v'achalnum b'lo melach
v'im achalnum b'melach kol shekein shehayu paneinu tzehubim, so yesterday we were
in the field and they brought before us תרדין, tardin, תרדין tardin
I think are large beets or rutabagas of some kind, and we
ate them without salt, and if we had eaten them with salt
then our faces would have been glowing even more.
המפרשים hamfarshim here seem to say this is a certain kind of
modesty, the reason his face was shining was because he's a big
תורה Torah scholar as we're going to see in the later lines
in the גמרא, Gemara, however he didn't want to embarrass his רבי
Rebbi Rabbi Tarfon and so he said it was because he ate
the rutabagas.
אמרה היא מטרוניתא לרבי יהודה, amra hi matronita l'Rabbi Yehuda, this woman
accused or said to Rabbi Yehuda it's a Latin word מטרוניתא, matronita,
matron, yeah exactly. So she says to Rabbi Yehuda, it comes across
all the all the time in the מדרשים midrashim and different things,
all the stories with you know an accomplished woman who comes to
see the rabbis, so she's always מטרוניתא, matronita, okay. So this woman
says to Rabbi Yehuda מורה ורבי, mora v'ravi, she's making almost a
pun on מורי ורבי mori v'rabbi my teacher, she says מורה ורבי,
mora v'ravi, are you teaching תורה Torah while you're drunk? She's accusing
him because why because his face was very glowing, he was blushing
perhaps something like this. אמר לה הימנותא בידא דההיא איתתא אי טעימנא
אלא קדושא ואבדלתא amar lah heimanuta b'yada d'hahi itata ei ta'imna ella
kiddusha v'avdalta וארבעה כסי דפסחא. v'arba kasse de-Pischa. Did I, have I
ever had any wine except for קידוש
Kiddush and הבדלה Havdalah and the four cups on פסח? Pesach? So
this is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda suggestion of how much wine to
drink is very little. You should have קידוש Kiddush and you should
have הבדלה Havdalah and the four cups on פסח. Pesach. And further
בכל גרוני צידי be-khol gronei tsidei מן הפסח ועד העצרת min ha-Pesach
ve-ad ha-Atzeret because he has such a bad headache from having had
four cups of wine. Yeah, so that's an important point about our
alcohol consumption that we should take note from רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
It often gets quoted
in the discussion of whether or not the wine that we use
for קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה Havdalah and four cups has to be
intoxicating or not. I think it was the בניין Binyan of רב
משה פיינשטיין, Rav Moshe Feinstein, which is that it must contain some
measure of alcohol, even if it's very lightly alcoholic, because of this
story of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who avoided alcohol at great costs, he didn't use grape juice, he
used wine. Presumably they would have been able to use grape juice.
So it sounds like from this that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who was a bit of a teetotaler except on when it was
needed for a מצוה, mitzvah, that he would have preferred grape juice,
he still didn't use the grape juice. So it says, אלא חכמת
אדם תאיר פניו. ella chokhmat adam ta'ir panav. He answers to this
woman, no, the reason why is because based on a פסוק pasuk
from קהלת Kohelet that the—a person's wisdom brightens the face. So since
I'm a big תורה Torah scholar, that's why my face is shining.
אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי לרבי יהודה, Amar lei hahu Tzeduki le-Rabbi Yehuda,
so a צדוקי Tzeduki said to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, פניך דומים
או כמלווי ריבית panekha domim o ke-malvei ribit או כמגדלי חזירים. o
ke-megadlei chazirim. Your face looks like either people who charge money—charge interest
for their loans, מלווי ריבית, malvei ribit, they lend with interest, או
כמגדלי חזירים, o ke-megadlei chazirim, or like people who raise pigs. It's
not clear to me why people who either charge interest or raise
pigs would have such a smiling, bright face. המפרש ha-mefaresh seems to
think that the reason why at least
the מלווי ריבית malvei ribit are so happy is because they make
a lot of money. They charge interest and they get, you know,
they get rich, so they're very happy all the time. I'm not
sure about why מגדלי חזירים, megadlei chazirim, why people who raise pigs
are so happy.
But yes, the image of משה Moshe when he comes down and
he has his shining—covered his face, so that—right, it's a similar image
here.
And I actually recently saw it on the—someone had written some kind
of a blog and they made a similar suggestion that that was
why הרב עובדיה זצ"ל, HaRav Ovadia zatzal, why רבי עובדיה Rabbi Ovadia
wore the red glasses was because he was trying to block the
light that was emanating from his face. I think it was a
bit extreme of veneration, but nonetheless הרב עובדיה HaRav Ovadia for sure,
you know. Anyway, you know, we say this about the תנאים, Tannaim,
we say this about משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, I don't know whether
it applies to big תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim in our day or
not, but that's a separate discussion. Okay. So, so what does he
say back? So אמר ליה ביהודאי תרווייהו אסירן. amar lei bi-yehudai tarveihu
asiran. No, both of those things are forbidden for Jewish people. He's
answering to the צדוקי. Tzeduki. Interestingly enough why the צדוקי Tzeduki is
accusing רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of breaking different הלכות, halakhot, it's interesting
to note, the debate who was firmer than whom. It seems like
the צדוקים Tzedukim tried to fancy themselves as more observant of הלכה
halakha than the early rabbis.
Obviously our tradition comes from the rabbinic traditions. It's an interesting point
about who was arguing with whom about different הלכות. halakhot. Very often
we see that the צדוקים Tzedukim were very strict about certain things
and the rabbis were intentionally lenient in order to show no, the
תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be-al peh allows us certain things that you
think from the פשט pshat in the תורה Torah doesn't apply. Okay.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
back, ביהודאי תרווייהו אסירן, bi-yehudai tarveihu asiran, for Jews, so Jews are
not allowed to do either of those two things, lend with interest
or raise pigs. אלא עשרין וארבעה בתי הכסא אית לי מן ביתא
לבי מדרשא. ella esrin ve-arba'ah batei ha-kisse it li min beita le-bei
midrasha. There are twenty-four latrines on the way from my house to
the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. דכל שעה ושעה, dekhol sha'ah ve-sha'ah, meaning
every chance I get, not every hour, but every chance I get,
אני נכנס לכל אחד ואחד. ani nikhnas le-khol echad ve-echad. As I
walk from my house to the בית מדרש Beit Midrash every day
to go, I use every one of the twenty-four public use latrines.
And that is why he was so happy or his face was
so shining bright. So let's stop there. One other point to note,
interestingly enough, we said that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda had the opinion
about drinking the wine for קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה. Havdalah. It's an
interesting מחלוקת machloket about whether wine is necessary for
קידוש Kiddush מדאורייתא mi-de'oraita or not. והגמרא בפסחים ve-ha-Gemara be-Pesachim says, זכור
את יום השבת לקדשו. zakhor et yom ha-Shabbat le-kaddesho. We have to
remember שבת Shabbat is the פסוק pasuk from the Ten
Commandments. והגמרא דורשת תנו רבנן, ve-ha-Gemara darshena tnu rabbanan, זכור את יום
השבת לקדשו זכרהו על היין. zakhor et yom ha-Shabbat le-kaddesho, zakhrehu al
ha-yayin. We have to mention it or remember it over wine. It
sounds like it's מדאורייתא. mi-de'oraita. It sounds like learned from the פסוק
pasuk of זכור. Zakhor. However, most of the opinions throughout the ראשונים
Rishonim particularly based on other גמרות Gemarot as well, take it as
only דרבנן de-rabbanan to have wine at קידוש. Kiddush. תוספות Tosafot in
פסחים Pesachim there suggests that holding a cup of wine during קידוש
Kiddush may be מדאורייתא mi-de'oraita but you don't have to drink it.
Only have to drink it מדרבנן. m'd'rabanan. And the מפרש Mefaresh in
מסכת נזיר, Masechet Nazir, towards the beginning, it'll be there relatively soon.
So the מפרש Mefaresh in נזיר, Nazir, who's not really רש״י, Rashi,
but it's a fake רש״י, Rashi, so he says yes, it is
a מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah d'oraita to have wine for קידוש. kiddush. So
with that we are close to the bottom of מ״ט עמוד ב׳,
mem tet amud bet, and we will pick up there tomorrow morning
at 7:30.
Is it known what you're saying that?